Guide to the Everett Education Association Records
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
- United Teachers of Everett records, circa 1971-1986; 1973-1986; 3849-002; 22.00 cubic feet
  - Everett Bargaining Election Part 2, 1975; Press releases, financial reports, newsletters, etc. regarding the bargaining election (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Mediation and Bargaining Information Part 1, 1976-1977; Financial reports, newsletters, local bargaining agreements, other district agreements, descriptions of proposals (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Mediation and Bargaining Information Part 2, 1976 - 1977; Counter proposals, definitions of terms in contracts, annotated versions of material in folder 9 with additional notes and memos (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Everett Contract Proposal Drafts Part 1, 1976; Drafts and annotations of contract proposal parts by sections that correspond to folder 8/9, some rough pages, mostly copies with handwritten notes (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Everett Contract Proposal Drafts Part 2, 1976; Drafts and annotations of contract proposal parts by sections that correspond to folder 8/9, some rough pages, mostly copies with handwritten notes (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Everett Contract Proposal Drafts Part 3, 1976; Drafts and annotations of contract proposal parts by sections that correspond to folder 8/9, some rough pages, mostly copies with handwritten notes (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Everett Teachers' Contract, 1975-1976; ¼ filled stenograph notebook regarding crisis bargaining process, copied pages of the faculty handbook, proposed full master contract from spring 1976, held together with metal screws (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Bargaining Memos and Proposals, 1976; Copies of memos regarding contracts and contract riders, certified employee contracts, copies of hand-written notes and counter-proposals (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Negotiation Session Minutes and Notes Part 1, 1976; Spiral notebook with hand-written notes from negotiation sessions, also with typed minutes for most meetings based off of notes (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Negotiation Session Minutes and Notes Part 2, 1976; Spiral notebook with hand-written notes from negotiation sessions and carbon copies of minutes in back of notebook (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Negotiation Session Minutes and Notes Part 3, 1976; Legal pad with hand-written notes from negotiation sessions 30 to 33 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Negotiation Session Minutes and Notes Part 4, 1976; Spiral notebook half filled with notes from meetings between the district and Everett Education Association (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Negotiation Session Minutes and Notes Part 5, 1976; Spiral notebook with notes from findings and research for contract negotiations (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - 1976-1977 Interim Contract and Rider, Teachers’ contract agreement while a new contract is discussed (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - District Contract Proposals and Counter-Proposals, 1976; Copies of proposals and counter proposals presented by the school district on a variety of subjects, collected by the Everett Education Association – with hand-written notes and some paperclip rust damage. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - District Fact Finding Information (Part 1), 1976; Evidence for Everett Education Association v. ESD court case in favor of the Everett School District regarding teachers’ salaries and experience in Washington. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - District Fact Finding Information (Part 2), 1976; Last proposals from ESD and Everett Education Association before court trial, collection and definition of issues that the ESD has failed to address, denied, or which the Everett Education Association has not addressed (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Pre Fact-Finding Court Documents, 1976; Court documents regarding the fact-finding process for the Everett Education Association and ESD outlining the issues and positions of each party (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Everett Education Association Fact-Finding Information, 1976; Binder put together by the Everett Education Association outlining each issue and the information on each issue that they have (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Everett School District Contract, 1976; Proposed Collective Bargaining Agreement, nondiscrimination act, individual rights, notes from negotiation sessions, and Everett Education Association master contract (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Everett Education Association Strike Issues, 1976; Annotated copy of district and Everett Education Association positions on contract issues, issues that led to a strike (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - District Strike Proposals, 1976; School District proposals to end the Everett Education Association strike, October 1976, three copies of two proposals (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Everett Education Association Strike Proposals, 1976; Everett Education Association strike-ending proposals from October 1976 and the back to work agreement between the Everett Education Association and ESD (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - End of Strike Information, 1976; Strike newsletters, hand-written notes about the strike, and two copies of the ESD teachers’ contract (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - District Negotiations Information, 1976; District proposals and negotiations, hand-written and copied positions, mostly in good condition, some torn corners (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Everett Education Association Bargaining and Negotiations, 1976; Collective Bargaining Agreement, negotiations notes with negotiation suggestions (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Everett Education Association Contract Proposal, 1978; Copy of full proposed contract, with terms and conditions of contract / specifics outlined and specified (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Everett Education Association Negotiations Staff, 1977; Contracts and correspondences regarding hiring of bargaining spokesman and assistant spokesman for 1978 contract negotiations (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Everett Education Association Contract Copy, 1978; Full contract for 1978-1979 school year, missing cover page (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Master Contract - Everett School District, 1976; Draft of the Everett School District contract for 1976-1978 school years (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Everett Education Association records, fall 1976, Copies of bargaining newsletters, school district contract proposals, Washington state law regarding teachers, and a court case regarding teaching methods (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Everett Education Association Contract Proposal, 1976; Contract proposals by section, copy of hand-written notes at the beginning and end of the collection (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Contract Revisions Part 1, 1976; Contract proposal, annotated and noted by section (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Contract Revisions Part 2, 1976; Contract proposal, annotated and noted by section (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Contract Revisions Part 3, 1976; Contract proposal, annotated and noted by section (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Negotiations and Contract Proposals, 1976; Information regarding the contract process, preliminary development information (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Proposed Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1976; Annotated and divided proposed collective bargaining agreement for 1976 contract, from May 1976, includes hand-written notes and many annotations (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Everett School District contract counter-proposals Part 1, 1976; Copies of counter- proposals for contract, many have other parts stapled on top of them and are layered with information (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Everett School District contract counter-proposals Part 2, 1976; Copies of counter- proposals for contract, many have other parts stapled on top of them and are layered with information (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - District Contract Counter-Proposals, 1976; Annotated copies of Everett School District counter proposals in contract negotiations, multiple parts stapled together (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Grievance Contract Information, 1976; Budget information, contractual grievance procedure – specified and annotated for teacher’s contract, with some annotation (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Everett Teachers Forms and Specific Contract Info, 1976; Contract duration, salary agreement, personnel file inventories, student behavior, and school calendars (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Benefit Proposals, 1976; Itemized list of district and Everett Education Association responsibilities, benefit packages proposals and counter-proposals (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Fact-finding Mediation Notes, 1976; Hand-written notebook describing and itemizing the mediation process, transcribed in many places, with detailed dates and times (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Mediation Notes, 1976; Hand-written notes outlining the mediation process, listed with session and date, in reverse chronological order (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Copies of Mediation Notes, 1976; Carbon copies and regular copies of notes from contract negotiation sessions, itemized by session (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Master Contract, 1976; Master contract agreed upon by the Everett Education Association and Everett School District for the 1976-1978 school years. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Everett Education Association Documents, Not available; Hand-written notes, newsletters, personal letters, and other papers and documents from the Everett Education Association (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Everett Education Association Contract Proposal, 1978; First draft of the proposed contract from the Everett Education Association with hand-written annotations (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Everett Education Association Contract Counterproposal, 1978; Minimal annotation of second draft of contract, with some tears and bent corners (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Counter Contract Proposals, 1978; Details of problems and information itemizing tentative agreements, and school board proposals (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Everett District Contract Information - 1978, District proposals, counter proposals, and memos regarding the budget and teachers’ salaries, analysis of contract proposals, list of certified employees (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Everett Education Association Meeting Notes – 1978, Handwritten notes from contract bargaining sessions and executive board meeting minutes and agendas, typed and hand-written (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Contract Negotiations Part 1, 1976-1978; Proposals to establish which parts of the contracts should be changed, and which ones should stay the same, lists of issues in dispute, list of staff seniority, correspondences related to bargaining, and rules regarding how bargaining records should be ke (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Contract Negotiations Part 2, 1976-1978; Proposals to establish which parts of the contracts should be changed, and which ones should stay the same, lists of issues in dispute, list of staff seniority, correspondences related to bargaining, and rules regarding how bargaining records should be ke (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Contract Negotiations Part 3, 1976-1978; Proposals to establish which parts of the contracts should be changed, and which ones should stay the same, lists of issues in dispute, list of staff seniority, correspondences related to bargaining, and rules regarding how bargaining records should be ke (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Bargaining Book 3, 1978; Hand-written notebook with transcription of contract negotiation meetings from August 16 to September 17 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Bargaining Book 2, 1978; Hand-written notebook with transcription of contract negotiation meetings from July 18 to August 11 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Bargaining Book 1, 1978; Hand-written notebook with transcription of contract negotiation meetings from May 9 to June 28 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Everett Contract Agreement, 1979; Official signed contract agreement between the Everett School District and the Everett Education Association (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1978; Two bound copies of the collective bargaining agreement between the Everett Education Association and the Everett School District for 1978-1980 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Proposed Master Contract, 1978; Two copies of the proposed master contract for the 1978 – 1981 school years, one with annotations and one without (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Contract Negotiations and Counter-proposals part 1, 1982; Copies of notes and hand-written letters with school schedules and hand-written annotations regarding the 1982 contract negotiations, some rust damage from paperclips (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Contract Negotiations and Counter-proposals part 2, 1982; Copies of notes and hand-written letters with school schedules and hand-written annotations regarding the 1982 contract negotiations, some rust damage from paperclips (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Bargaining Guides, Undated; “Getting Ready to Bargain” book produced by the WEA and summary of key provisions in the 1978-1980 collective bargaining agreement produced by the WEA (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Proposed Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1981; Annotated Proposed Collective Bargaining Agreement from the Everett Education Association to the Everett School District (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Reduction of Force Plans, 1982; Reduction of force plans and teacher evaluation methods and forms, letters, and memos (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bargaining Regarding Salary, 1981; Special Alert about bargaining, handwritten note and bargaining structure and timeline information (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Washington State House Bill 166, 1981; Washington State law regarding school budgets and bargaining, responses from Washington State Secretary of Education and Washington Education Association (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Contract Extensions and Amendment, 1981; Contract amendments and memos with hand-written notes (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Contract Analysis, Undated; Comments on contract amendments and analysis form from the Everett Education Association Contract Analysis Committee (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Formal Bargaining Information and analysis, 1981; Bargaining meeting minutes and agendas, formal bargaining analysis and agendas (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1979; Collective bargaining agreement information: memos, final document, teachers’ salary information (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Starting Contract Negotiations, 1979-1980; Negotiations guidelines and start of negotiations especially regarding school calendar negotiations (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Contract Issues in Dispute, 1976; List of issues in dispute, impact analysis, description of proposals and district / Everett Education Association positions on them, some rust damage (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Contract Agreement Analysis, 1981; Contract agreements, Special Ed. information funding plan, staff survey rough draft, bargaining agreement analysis form, contract committee survey information (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1980; Copy of the collective bargaining agreement between the Everett Education Association and Everett School District (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining Flyers, Undated; 3 copies of bargaining alert regarding Engrossed Substitute House Bill 166, regarding salary increases and benefits (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Contract Reduction in Force Debate, 1981-1982; Memos from Washington Education Association, meeting agendas, hand-written notes and copies of hand-written notes, contract analysis survey, class schedules, newsletters (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Contract Analysis Summary, Undated; Outline of contract provisions with comments and ways to change them (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Pilchuck Bargaining Agreement, 1981; Newsletters and bargaining handbooks (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Collective Bargaining Agreement, 1978; Official collective bargaining agreement between the Everett Education Association and Everett School district for the 1978-1980 school years (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Contract Development Worksheets, 1981; Hand-written notes on worksheets and notebook paper in pen and pencil (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Everett Education Association Policy Documents, 1979-1980; Collective Bargaining Agreement, Everett Education Association Bi-Laws, and Everett Education Association teachers’ handbook (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Bargaining Agreement Analysis Tools, Undated; Two blank copies of survey used to fix collective bargaining agreements (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Budget Newsletters, 1979; Newsletters from Everett Education Association regarding budget outlines and funding. (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Everett Education Association Request for new members, 1979; Everett Education Association request to Everett school district for information on new teachers, hand –written documents and half typed half hand-written documents. (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Contract Development Committee, 1980; Multiple copies of documents from the Contract Development Committee including meeting minutes, agendas, and memos (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Legislation and Contract Negotiations, 1979-1981; Laws, notes, memos, and surveys regarding student behavior and contract negotiations, Substitute House Bill 1676, hand-written and printed (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Everett Education Association Contract and Handbooks, 1982; Specific sections of Everett Education Association contract, with some corrections, Washington Education Association staff association handbook, summary of Everett Education Association/UTE position at the beginning of mediation booklet (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Letters Part 1, 1981-1984; Copies of hand-written notes, legal cases, bargaining handbook, Pilchuck Uni-serve info, budget info from other school districts, hand-written letters and newsletters, multiple sizes, no date order (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Letters Part 2, 1981-1984; Copies of hand-written notes, legal cases, bargaining handbook, Pilchuck Uni-serve info, budget info from other school districts, hand-written letters and newsletters, multiple sizes, no date order (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Contract Negotiations Information Part 1, 1981-1982; Contract information and pieces, negotiation offers, hand-written analysis (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Contract Negotiations Information Part 2, 1981-1982; Contract information and pieces, negotiation offers, hand-written analysis (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Contract Negotiations Information Part 3, 1981-1982; Contract information and pieces, negotiation offers, hand-written analysis (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Contract Negotiations Information Part 4, 1981-1982; Contract information and pieces, negotiation offers, hand-written analysis (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Out-of District Contract Information, 1984; Contract information for other school districts that the Everett Education Association intends to use in bargaining process, typed copies, one hand-written letter (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Everett Education Association Positions, 1983-1984; Fact-finding surveys, copies of hand-written contract provisions, Everett Education Association position papers on sections of the contract, (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Contract Negotiation Ballots, 1984; Ballots and ballot counts for contract ratification (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining strategy notes, 1982; Hand-written outline of what needs to be done for the bargaining process (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining Proposals, 1983-1984; Bargaining proposals, staff calendar, multiple copies and hand-written outlines, Everett Education Association and Everett School District court case (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Everett Teacher Aide Association Contract Agreement, 1981; Full contract agreement between Everett School District and Everett Teachers Aide Association for the 1981-1984 school years (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Contract Analysis Committee Notes, 1983-1985; Parts of documents to be photo-copied, hand-written notes, some documents with rust damage from paper clips (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining Team Thank You Notes, Undated; Thank you notes and notes of support to the Everett Education Association bargaining committee, hand-written (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Everett Education Association Assessment Forms, 1983; Surveys of teachers by school, both copies and hand-written, no details of the questions (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Bargaining Alert Notes, 1983; Bargaining Alert with notes / comments on the bottom (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Bargaining Notes, 1985; Short hand-written bargaining notes (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Contract Newsletters, 1984-1985; Know Your Contract flyers with comments, hand-written notes and explanations with each of these (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Mukilteo Education Association Bi-Laws, Undated; Copy of the bi-laws for the Mukilteo Education association, glue stain on the first page (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Benefit Questions, 1973-1974; Letters to the Everett School District regarding benefits and availability (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Initiative 276 Notes, 1974; Hand-written analysis of Initiative 276, and definition of “public records” (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Student Rights and Responsibilities, 1973; Two booklets of recommendations for Student Rights and Responsibilities handbook, and a legal overview of what students’ rights and responsibilities are (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - News Articles, Undated; Copies of articles in various publications from around 1970-1973, but inconclusive, regarding teachers’ rights and women’s rights in the work place (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Senator Jack Metcalf Placement Complaint, 1974; Handwritten note regarding Senator Metcalf’s placement history, 1969-1973 and memo regarding complaint (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Initiative 276 memos, 1972-1973; Copies and hand-written notes and memos to Washington State legislators regarding Initiative 276 (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Ridgefield Education Association Court Case, 1977; Court case regarding unfair labor practices in the Ridgefield School District, with a memo regarding significance (Box 12, Folder 27)
  - Evaluation Criteria Memos, 1973; two copies of a set of memos regarding how the Everett School District will evaluate teachers, and the legal precedent to do so (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - Everett Education Association Scholarship Information, 1969-1974; Letters to scholarship winners, colleges attended, sponsors, etc. regarding scholarship wins. (Box 12, Folder 29)
  - Snohomish County Needs Assessment, 1980; Booklet outlining household incomes, taxes paid, school district information, etc. (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - School Board Election Information, 1973; Candidate interviews, memos, newspaper clippings and advertisements regarding school board candidates some newspaper clippings stuck together (Box 12, Folder 31)
  - School Board Proposals for discharges / layoffs, 1973-1974; Legal documents outlining Everett School Districts right to personnel changes (Box 12, Folder 32)
  - Washington State Title IX, Undated; Legal notes and bill for Title IX to be approved in Washington state (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - Affirmative Action in Everett School District, 1974-1976; Handbook and memos on ways to implement affirmative action in the Everett School District (Box 12, Folder 34)
  - Leadership Information, Undated; Local Association newsletters, rules on parliamentary procedures, and other leadership aid materials (Box 12, Folder 35)
  - Layoff Information, Undated; List of salaries, years of experience, extra credits, etc. most without names, and a few memos regarding who should get laid off (Box 12, Folder 36)
  - Collective Bargaining, 1975; Newspaper clipping and memo regarding collective bargaining and the role of unions in society (Box 12, Folder 37)
  - School Calendar Debate, 1977; Memos, surveys, meeting minutes, and calendar outlines for the 1978-1979 school year regarding new laws that change the calendar (Box 12, Folder 38)
  - Extra-Curricular Pay Information, 1974; Hand-written notes, memos, pay scales, and handbooks regarding pay for coaches and other afterschool activity advisors (Box 12, Folder 39)